Estabrook, Arthur H.; Papers apap069
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
- Clippings, 1912-1936; Undated; 7
  - 1922-1924, 7.1 (Box 2 (7-Clippings), Folder 14)
    - i. "State Registrar Plecker Comments On Criticism of Virginia's Efforts To Enforce Racial Integrity Law".The News Leader, Richmond, 1924 September 9
    - j. "Robeson Expects A Monster Fair".The News and Observer, 1924 October 13
  - 1925, 7.2 (Box 2 (7-Clippings), Folder 15)
    - a. "Shall We All Be Mulattos?"The Literary Digest, p. 23-24, 1925 March 7
    - b. "Plecker Aroused By Blow Aimed At Racial Law".Richmond Times-Dispatch, 3-31-1925
    - c. "Places Indians in Negroid Class".The Richmond News Leader, 1925 July 2
    - d. Beirne, Francis F. "The Late South".The Evening Sun, Baltimore, 1925 July 2
    - e. "Pamunkey Chief Answers Plecker".The Richmond News Leader, 1925 July 8
  - 1926, 7.3 (Box 3 (7-Clippings), Folder 1)
    - a.The Indian Leader, v. 29, no. 17: 113-18, 1926 January 1
    - b. Mac Neill, Ben Dixon. "Riddle of The Lumbee Indians".The News and Observer, Raleigh, 1926 January 31; 1926 February 7; 1926 February 14; 1926 February 21
    - c. "Proposed Law Classes 20,000 Noted Virginians As 'Colored'".Baltimore Sun, 1926 February 9
    - d. "Know the Facts", 02/16/1926
    - e. Tucker, Harry. "Main Street". [Richmond Times-Dispatch], 02/16/1926
    - f. "Resolutions Oppose Pending Racial Bills". [Richmond Times-Dispatch], 02/17/1926
    - g. Motte. "The Capitol Square". [Richmond Times-Dispatch], 02/17/1961
    - h. McDougle, Ivan E. "The Color P roblem". [Letter to the editor], [Richmond Times-Dispatch], 1926 February 20
    - i. Says Integrity Bill Is Not Harsh".Richmond Times-Dispatch, 02/21/1926
    - j. Fragment:"... ginia men must get ready..".Richmond Times-Dispatch 2[?] 21, [1926]
    - k. "The Color Problem". Richmond Times-Dispatch, [February [?] 1926
    - l. "Virginia Not So Slow". Richmond Times-Dispatch, 1926 February 22
    - m. Mabane, Mary. "An American Problem" [Voice of the People]Richmond Times Dispatch, 02/24/1926
    - n. Montague, R. Cary. "A Real Remedy". [Voice of the People]Richmond Times-Dispatch, 02/24/1926
    - o. Wingo, Donald C. "Down to Brass Tacks". [Voice of the People]Richmond Times-Dispatch, 02/26/1926
    - p. Coghill, H. D. "The Only Effective Remedy". [Voice of the People]Richmond Times-Dispatch, 02/26/1926
    - q. "Says Mixed Races Would End Strife".Philadelphia Record, 1926 February
    - r. Davis, M. B. "A Mother's Standpoint". [Letters Richmond Times-Dispatch, 1926 February 28
    - s. Williams, W. R, "Face the Facts Like Men". [Letters]Richmond Times-Dispatch, 1926 February 28
    - t. Richardson, W. G. "Evading the Issue". [Letters]Richmond Times-Dispatch, 1926 February 28
    - u. Owen, Mrs. R. J. "From a 'Grandma'". Voice of the People] [Richmond Times-Dispatch, 03/01/1961
    - v. "Discuss Segregation at Colored Meeting".Richmond Times-Dispatch, 03/01/1926
    - w. "For Racial Integrity".Richmond Times-Dispatch, 03/02/1926
    - x. "N. Y. State Senator Asks For Integrity Bill Information".Richmond Times-Dispatch, 1926 March 4
    - y. Copeland, W. S., "Pass the Massenburg Bill". [Voice of the People]Richmond Times-Dispatch, 03/04/1926
    - z. "Noted Citizens Sign For Racial Integrity Bill".Richmond Times-Dispatch, 1926 March 4
    - aa. "Make Racial Integrity Bill Acceptable, Aim".Richmond Times-Dispatch, 1926 March 5
    - bb. Powell, John. "For Sake of Justice". [Voice of the People]Richmond Times-Dispatch, 1926 March 5
    - cc. "The Massenburg Bill".Richmond Times-Dispatch, 1926 March 5
    - dd. "House Passes Racial and Two Rail Measures".Richmond Times-Dispatch, 1926 March 7
    - ee. Harrison, E.L.. "What Possible Objection?" [Letter to the editor]Richmond Times-Dispatch, 1926 March 6
    - ff. "The Crux of the Matter".Richmond Times-Dispatch, 1926 March 7
    - gg. "The Real Trouble". Richmond Times-Dispatch, 1926 March 9
    - hh. "Racial Integrity Bill Meets Death When Senate Votes to Postpone Action Indefinitely. "Richmond Times-Dispatch, 1926 March 13
    - ii. "The Rhinelander Case".Richmond Times-Dispatch, 1926 March 29
    - jj. "Indian School Case Results in Mistrial".The Robesonian, 1926 May 20
    - kk. "Two Indians Shoot Up Store At Pembroke and Run Folks Away". The Robesonian, 10/01/1926
    - ll. Oxendine, Griffan.- "Men Who Shot up Store Not Recognized As Indians of Robeson". [Letter]The Robesonian, 10-?-1926
  - Powell, John. "The Last Stand", 1926 (Box 3 (7-Clippings), Folder 2)
    Richmond Times-Dispatch, February 16-18, [undated], 22, [23], 24, [25?], 26, [undated], March 1, 1926. Love. L.F. "The Last Stand". [Letter to the editor] Richmond Times-Dispatch, February 22, 1926.
  - The Jukes, 7.5 (Box 3 (7-Clippings), Folder 3)
    - a. "Degenerate Family Cost State Heavily", 1912 January 18
    - b. "Carrie Maines" (Death notice) Leader, 11-16-1926
    - c. "Jukeses Mentality Unfit for Crimes of Today", [New York Evening Post], 1933 October 16
  - Reviews of Mongrel Virginians, 7.6 (Box 3 (7-Clippings), Folder 4)
    - a. The Williams & Wilkins Company. "Mongrel Virginians", (leaflet), 1936
    - b. "Mongrel Virginians"The American Journal of Sociology, Undated; typescript
    - c. Estabrook, A. H. and McDougle, Ivan E. "Mongrel Virginians"The Annals of the American Academy, 165-166, Undated
    - d. "Mongrel"British Medical Journal, 1928 December 4
    - e. "Mongrel Virginians: The Win Tribe".Mental Hygiene, 640-43, Undated
    - f. "Mongrel Virginians: The Win Tribe".Nature, 1927 June 4
    - g. "Mongrel Virginians"News, Lynchburg, Virginia, 1926 April 29
  - Berea College, 7.7 (Box 3 (7-Clippings), Folder 5)
    - a. "10 Berea Students Here For Five Days".The New York Times, 1926 June 6
    - b. Berea College, Information Card, Undated
    - c. Winter, Alice Ames. "Berea". n.p., Undated
  - Miscellaneous and undated, 7.8 (Box 3 (7-Clippings), Folder 6)
    - a. "The Gullah-speaking..."
    - b. "Virginia Dare's County to Salute Her"
    - c. "She's Expert at Several Pursuits"
    - d. "Negro 'Who's Who' To Be Published Here"
    - e. "Hold Lenten Services For South Side Children"
    - f. "With the Guineamen of Virginia"
    - g. "Compulsory Education Law for Children Between 8 and 14 Passed"
    - h. "Maryland's Wesorts Are A 'Different' People". "Tennessee Bars Evolution From Public Schools"
    - i. Scarborough, Dorothy. "Where the Eighteenth Century Lives On".The New York Times Book Review, 1931 December 27
    - j. Lieberman, Elias. "On the Turning Up of the Kaiser's Skull".New York Times, 1917 July
- Miscellaneous Publications by Others, 1914; 1917; 1922; 1924-1926; 8
  - a. Hunter, Walter S., assisted by Eloise Sommermier. "The Relation of Degree of Indian Blood to Score on the Otis Intelligence Test". from The Journal of Comparative Psychology, v. 2, no. 3, p. 257-277, 1922 June (Box 3 (8-Miscellaneous Publications by Others), Folder 7)
  - b. White America Society.White America by Earnest Sevier Cox. [publisher's leaflet] [4] p., ca. 1926 (Box 3 (8-Miscellaneous Publications by Others), Folder 7)
    **Added (from unknown source): Cox, E. S. The South's Part in Mongrelizing the Nation. Richmond: White America Society.
  - c. "Intermarriage: Standpoint and Tentative Questionnaire" (Box 3 (8-Miscellaneous Publications by Others), Folder 7)
  - d. Pleeker, W. A. "The New Virginia Law To Preserve Racial Integrity".Virginia Health Bulletin, v. 16, extra no. 2, 4 p., 1924 March (Box 3 (8-Miscellaneous Publications by Others), Folder 7)
  - e. "Registration of Birth and Color". Form 59 - 3-17-24 - 65M (Box 3 (8-Miscellaneous Publications by Others), Folder 7)
  - f. Wormeley, Carter W. "Illegitimate Births in Virginia Discussed by Head of Vital Statistics" 1 f., 1924 September 11 (Box 3 (8-Miscellaneous Publications by Others), Folder 7)
  - g.The New Family and Race Improvement. New Family Series, no. 5. Richmond, Va.: State Board of Health, Bureau of Vital Statistics, 1925; [32] p. (Box 3 (8-Miscellaneous Publications by Others), Folder 7)
  - h.George Hunter's Map of the Cherokee Country and the Path thereto in 1730, with comments by A. S. Salley, Jr. Bulletin of the Historical Commission of South Carolina, no. 4. Columbia, S. C.: The State Company, 1917 (Box 3 (8-Miscellaneous Publications by Others), Folder 7)
  - i. U.S. Geological Survey.Reconnaissance Map: Virginia, Lexington Sheet. Edition of September 1894, reprinted 1914. 1 sheet (Box 3 (8-Miscellaneous Publications by Others), Folder 7)
- Carrie Buck Trial, 1924-1927; 9
  Materials on the 1924 Supreme Court case against the Virginia statute of sterilization of the mentally defective.
  - Correspondence, 9.1 (Box 3 (9-Carrie Buck Trial), Folder 8)
    - a. [Strode, Aubrey E.], 1924 September 30
      Letter, to Dr. H. H. Laughlin., Cold Spring Harbor, Long Island, N. Y. Carbon of typescript. 2 p.
    - b. Strode, Aubrey E., 1924 October 10
      Letter, Lynchburg, Va., to Dr. Arthur H. Estabrook, Cold Spring Harbor, Long Island, N. Y. Carbon of typescript, signed. 1p.
    - c. Estabrook, Jessie, 1924 October 23
      Telegram, Mt. Washington, Md., to Dr. Arthur O. H. Estabrook. Typescript. 1 p.
    - d. Strode, Aubrey E., 1924 October 29
      Letter, Lynchburg, Va., to Dr. A. H. Estabrook, Hyden, Ky. Typescript, signed. 1p.
    - e. [Strode, Aubrey E.], 1924 November 5
      Letter, to Dr. H. H. Laughlin, Cold Spring Harbor, Long Island, N. Y. Carbon of typescript. 1p.
    - f. Strode, Aubrey E., 1924 November 6
      Letter, Lynchburg, Va., to Dr. Arthur H. Estabrook, Hyden, Ky. Typescript, signed. 1p.
    - g. Estabrook, Arthur H., 1924 November 8
      Letter, Hyden, Ky., to Mr. Aubrey Strode, Lynchburg, Va. Carbon of typescript. 1p.
    - h. Strode, Aubrey E., 1924 November 15
      Letter, Lynchburg, Va., to Dr. A. H. Estabrook, Charlottesville, Va. Typescript, signed. 1p.
    - i. Strode, Aubrey E., 1924 December 11
  - Photographs, 1924 (Box 3 (9-Carrie Buck Trial), Folder 9)
    Carrie Buck, Emma Buck; Carrie's baby... with Mrs. John Dobbs.
    - Photograph of Carrie and Emma Buck, 1924
    - Additional album pages, 1924
  - Strode, Aubrey E. "Sterilization of Defectives". In Virginia Law Review v. 11 no. 4, 296-301, 1925 February (Box 3 (9-Carrie Buck Trial), Folder 10)
  - Court records, 9.4 (Box 3 (9-Carrie Buck Trial), Folder 11)
    - a. In the Supreme Court of Appeals of Virginia at Staunton: Carrie Buck... vs. Dr. J. H. Bell. From the Circuit Court of Amherst County
    - b. In the Supreme Court of Appeals of Virginia at Staunton, September Term, JOIN 1925. Carrie Buck vs. Dr. J. H. Bell. Brief for Appellee. Sterilization of Hereditary Defectives. The Limits of the Power of the State over the Propagation of the Unfit
    - c. In the Supreme Court of Appeals of Virginia at Staunton. September Term, 1925
      Carrie Buck... vs. Dr. J. H. Bell. Reply Brief for Appellant.
    - d. Supreme Court of the United States. October Term, 1926
      Carrie Buck... vs. J. H. Bell.
  - Clipping. "Sterilization of Defectives, Aim".Richmond Courier Journal, 05/27/1927 (Box 3 (9-Carrie Buck Trial), Folder 12)
- Venereal Disease Campaign, 1924-1925; 1929-1930; 1936; Undated; 10
  Material from the Bellevue-Yorkville Health Demonstration in New York City in October, November, and December of 1930.
  - "Calendar -- Social Hygiene Education Campaign -- 1930" (Box 3 (10-Venereal Disease Campaign), Folder 13)
  - Office folder of form letters, items distributed, clippings, press releases, etc. (Box 3 (10-Venereal Disease Campaign), Folder 14)
  - Press releases (Box 3 (10-Venereal Disease Campaign), Folder 15)
  - Clippings (Box 3 (10-Venereal Disease Campaign), Folder 16)
  - Publications (Box 3 (10-Venereal Disease Campaign), Folder 17)
    a. University of Minnesota. Social Hygiene Bureau. "Questions Submitted by Minneapolis Visiting Nurses...".
    b. Missouri Social Hygiene Association. "Suggestions for Including All Phases of Social Hygiene in the School of Nursing Curriculum".
  - Publications of The American Social Hygiene Association (Box 3 (10-Venereal Disease Campaign), Folder 18)
    a. List of publications, etc.
    b. Child Questions and Their Answers.
    c. Sex Education.
    d. Social Hygiene Publications.
  - Publications by Walter M. Brunet (Box 3 (10-Venereal Disease Campaign), Folder 19)
    a. Gonorrhea in the Female.
    b. Venereal Disease Prevalence in the City of New York: I. Richmond County (Staten Island).
    c. II. Kings County (Brooklyn).
    d. III. Bronx County.
    e. IV. Queens County (Long Island).
    f. V. New York County (Manhattan).
  - Publications (Box 3 (10-Venereal Disease Campaign), Folder 20)
    a. The Committee on Venereal Disease of the Charity Organization Society. The Social Workers Approach to the Problem of Venereal Disease.
    b. New York City Commission to Investigate the Prevention and Control of Syphilis and Gonorrhea in Scandinavian Countries and in Great Britain. Report.
    c. The New York Medical Week, December 27, 1930.
    d. Snow, William F. Venereal Diseases: Their Medical, Nursing, and Community Aspects. New York and London: Funk & Wagnalls Company, ca. 1924.
  - 3 posters advertising health awareness meetings, Undated (Oversized 1)
- Crippled Children in Buffalo and Erie County, 1936; 1943; 1947; 11
  The Council of Social Agencies of Buffalo requested a survey of the problem of crippled children in Buffalo and Erie County with particular reference to the part the Crippled Children's Guild should play in the situation.
  - Estabrook, Arthur H. "The Crippled Children Situation in Buffalo and Erie County. Survey Made at the Request of The Council of Social Agencies of Buffalo and Erie County", copy of typescript (Box 4 (11-Crippled Children in Buffalo and Erie County), Folder 1)
  - St. Nicholas Clinic, 11.2 (Box 4 (11-Crippled Children in Buffalo and Erie County), Folder 2)
    - a. "Diagnosis and Recommendations", 05/22/1936
    - b. Report sheets
    - c. Memorandum, "Crippled Individuals Under State Supervision", 1936 May 23
  - Correspondence, 11.3 (Box 4 (11-Crippled Children in Buffalo and Erie County), Folder 3)
    - a. Jarnagin, Rufus, 1936 June 25
      Letter, Buffalo, N. Y., to Mr. Paul L. Benjamin, Buffalo, N. Y. Carbon of typescript. 1 l.
    - b. Arnold, Mary, 1936 July 9
      Letter, New York, N. Y., to Dr. Arthur H. Estabrook, New York, N. Y. Typescript, signed. 1 l.
    - c. Estabrook, Arthur H., 1936 July 10
      Letter, to Mrs. J. P. Devine, Buffalo, N. Y. Carbon of typescript 1 l.
    - d. Foster, James H., 1936 July 21
      Letter, Albany, N. Y. to Mr. Arthur H. Estabrook, New York, N. Y. Typescript, signed. 1 l.
  - Clippings and publications, 11.4 (Box 4 (11-Crippled Children in Buffalo and Erie County), Folder 4)
    - a. "Men's Executive Board to Be Formed by Crippled..".Buffalo Courier-Express, 1936 June 27
    - b. Ware, E. Louise.Mental Hygiene of the Orthopedically' Handicapped Child. New York: Association for the Aid of Crippled Children, 1947
    - c.Medical Information for Vocational Rehabilitation Officers. Washington., D. G.: U.S. Government Printing Office, 1943
- Housing Study, Buffalo, 1930; 1943; Undated; 12
  - Estabrook, Arthur H.A Roof Over Their Heads. What's What in Housing in Buffalo. Carbon of typescript. 112; additional, copy of p. 10-14: "Buffalo Municipal Housing Authority", 1943 (Box 4 (12-Housing Study, Buffalo), Folder 5)
  - Notes, 1943 (Box 4 (12-Housing Study, Buffalo), Folder 6)
  - Publications of Buffalo agencies, Undated (Box 4 (12-Housing Study, Buffalo), Folder 7)
  - Publications by Pennsylvania Conference on Housing, Undated (Box 4 (12-Housing Study, Buffalo), Folder 8)
  - Miscellaneous, 1930; 12.5 (Box 4 (12-Housing Study, Buffalo), Folder 9)
    - a. Southern Women's Educational Alliance, 1930 October 3
      Copy of form letter. 1 l.
    - b. "Report of a Conference in regard to the Desirability of a Cooperative Survey of the Southern Mountains", 3 p.
    - c. Items laid Hollander.Brain and Intelligence
    - d. Corrections. Penciled note on corrections
- Publications by Estabrook, 1912; 1920; 1923; 1926; 13
  Please note that the archivist removed the geneological key and photographs from The Nam Family: A Study in Cacogenics for preservation purposes. These items are now stored in box 4, folder 10.
  - Accompanying Photographs and Key to the Nam Family from Estabrook, Arthur H., and Davenport, Charles B.The Nam Family: A Study in Cacogenics (Box 4 (13-Publications by Estabrook), Folder 10)
  - Estabrook's personal copy of the The Nam Family: A Study in Cacogenics (Box 5 (13-Publications by Estabrook))
  - Estabrook, Arthur H. "Report of a Study of Mental Ability of Children in One Orphan's Home in Indiana". from The Proceedings of the Indiana Academy of Science, p. 69-70, 1920 (Box 4 (13-Publications by Estabrook), Folder 11)
  - Estabrook, Arthur H. "The Tribe of Ishmael". from Eugenics, Genetics and the Family, v. 1, p. 398-404, 1923 (Box 4 (13-Publications by Estabrook), Folder 11)
  - Mongrel Virginians, News Clippings, 1926 (Box 4 (13-Publications by Estabrook), Folder 12)
- Research Material, 1908-1962; 14
  Many of the published resources acquired from Estabrook were separated from the manuscript collection and are being cataloged in the University Libraries' online catalog. Contact a member of the Department's staff for additional information or to obtain a complete list of titles donated by Estabrook. Please note the dates for this series are not inclusive.
  - Hospital Planning, 1912; 1920; 1923; 1926 (Box 4 (14-Research Material), Folder 13)
    Hospital Facilities Section, U.S. Public Health Service. Technical Hospital and Health Center Planning Material Request.
    The Bulletin of the Hospital Council of Greater New York.
    Lublin, Alfred M. Health Center, Elizabeth City, New Jersey.
    McGibony, J. R. Health Center Designed for Rural Needs.
    Hospital Facilities Section, U.S. Public Health Service. Planning for Integrated Service: A Health Center Unit.
    Hospital Facilities Section, U.S. Public Health Service. Modern Standards in Adequate Facilities for Obstetric Care.
    Dunham, Ethel. Standard Plans for Nurseries for Newborn in Hospitals of 50 to 200 Beds.
    Marysville Community Hospital. The Hospital: A Line Assembly for Medical Care.
    Hospital Facilities Section, U.S. Public Health Service. A Type Plan for a Pediatric Hospital Unit.
    Hospital Facilities Section, U.S. Public Health Service. New Plan Standards For Hospital Nurseries.
    Hospital Facilities Section, U.S. Public Health Service. Planning for Integrated Service: The District Hospital.
  - Halsey, George A.The Negro in America, Six Part Radio Program produced by Voice of America, 1962 (Box 4 (14-Research Material), Folder 14)
    1. Negro Educational Opportunities, Dr. George Eaton Simpson, Oberlin College.
    2. Negor Voting Rights in teh South, Harold C. Fleming, Executive Vice President, The Potomac Institute.
    3. The Supreme Court, Tradition, and the States, Dr. Guy B. Johnson, University of North Carolina.
    4. Tensions and Change in Negro-White Relations, Harry Ashmore, Editor-in-Chief, Encyclopedia Britannica, Former Editor, Little Rock Gazette.
    5. Reflections from the Deep South, Ralph McGill, Editor, the Atlanta Constitution.
    6. One Year's Progress in Civil Rights, Roy Wilkins, Executive Secretary, NAACP.
  - U.S. Congress Housing Act of 1950, 1944-1945 (Box 4 (14-Research Material), Folder 15)
    Land Assembly for Urban Development, 1945.
    Publications of Interest to Suburbanites and Home Builders, 1944.
  - Laughlin, H. H. Eugenics in America, 1925 (Box 4 (14-Research Material), Folder 16)
    Davenport, Chas. B. Chromosomes, Endocrines and Heredity, 1925.
    Lamb, Robert B. Habeas Corpus Proceedings in Lunacy Cases, 1908.
    Williams, Tom A. The Craving for the Supernatural, 1916.
    McKee, A. E. State Will Work to Aid Its Wards, 1913.
  - The Training School Bulletin, 1910-1930 (Box 4 (14-Research Material), Folder 17)
    The Training School Bulletin, Vol. VII, No. 5, September 1910.
    Doll, Edgar A. "School Training of Exceptional Children in Rural Districts". Reprint from The Training School Bulletin, June 1928.
    Doll, Edgar A. "Department of Research Annual Report, 1928-1929, Part I". Reprint from The Training School Bulletin, February-March 1930.
  - Davenport, C. B. Medico-Legal Aspects of Eugenics, 1914 (Box 4 (14-Research Material), Folder 18)
    Woods, F. A. Successful Men Have Larger Families, 1928.
    Laughlin, Harry H. Eugenical Sterilization in the U.S., 1920.
    Butler, F. O. A Quarter of a Century's Experience in Sterilization of Mental Defectives in California, 1945.
    Phelan, Daniel. The Mental Factor in Crime, 1913.
    Dayton, Neil. Influence of Size of Family upon the Characteristics of the Mentally Deficient, 1935.
  - Summer, Helen L. Standards Applicable to Child Labor, 1917 (Box 4 (14-Research Material), Folder 19)
    Summer, Helen L. Standards Applicable to Child Labor, 1917.
    Hickson, Wm. J. Psychiatry and Sociology, 1917.
    Hickson, Wm. J. Organic Brain Lesions in Mental Defectives, 1914.
    Pollock, Horatio M. A Statistical System for the Use of Institutions for Criminals and Delinquents, 1920.